{"tossups": [{"question": "<b><u>This person presided over the case of</u> </b><em><b><u>United States v. Bright</u></b></em><b><u>, in which position he held that</u></b> <b><u>Brigadier General Michael Bright was guilty of violating federal law after disregarding the Supreme</u></b> <b><u>Court\u2019s ruling in</u> </b><em><b><u>United States v. Peters</u></b></em><b><u>. This justice, who was appointed by (+)</u> John Adams, authored the </b><em><b>Green v. Biddle</b></em><b> decision, which invalidated numerous laws protecting Kentucky settlers from absentee landlords. (*) </b>For the points, name this Supreme Court justice from 1799 to 1829 who inherited Mount Vernon from his uncle.", "answer": "<b><u>B</u></b>ushrod <b><u>Washington</u></b> (prompt on \"Washington\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Forces loyal to this person operated out of the region of Las Segovias. Adolfo Diaz was opposed</u></b> <b><u>by this person, who called for the renunciation of the Bryan-Chamorro Treaty, which granted the</u></b> <b><u>United States rights to build a (+)</u> canal in his country. The </b><em><b>Indigenismo</b></em><b> ideology influenced this leader, whose supporters would later ally with the Junta for National Reconstruction and later be led by longtime leader Daniel (*) </b>Ortega. For the points, name this Nicaraguan revolutionary and inspiration for the name of a socialist party.", "answer": "Augusto C\u00e9sar <b><u>Sandino</u></b> (or Augusto Nicol\u00e1s Calder\u00f3n <b><u>Sandino</u></b> \u2013 do not accept or prompt on \u201cSandinista\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>According to workers, this event may have occurred due to the Wormit foundry's use of</u></b> <b><u>\"Cleveland Iron.\" Henry Law investigated this event, in which 75 people died, and one poem about</u></b> <b><u>this event ends with the lines, (+)</u> \"For the stronger we our houses do build/The less chance we have of being killed,\" and says that this event \"will be remember\u2019d for a very long time.\" (*) </b>For the points, name this 1879 engineering disaster over the namesake firth in Scotland, the subject of an infamously bad poem by William Topaz McGonagall.", "answer": "<b><u>Tay Bridge</u></b> Disaster (accept synonyms such as <b><u>Collapse</u></b> in place of \"Disaster\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The Naryn-Kala citadel is located in one city in this region which has been continually</u></b> <b><u>inhabited since at least the 8th century BC. The Abbasid caliph Harun al-Rashid once lived in this</u></b> <b><u>republic's city of Derbent, (+)</u> and the city of Samandar in this modern republic was the capital of Khazaria. Sergey Melikov is the current head of this republic, whose contemporary borders include parts of Terek Oblast. The Avars are the largest ethnic group of, (*) </b>for the points, what majority-Muslim Russian republic, which is governed from Makhachkala?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Dagestan</u></b> (or Respublika <b><u>Dagestan</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Lord Halifax purchased a painting by Joshua Reynolds that depicts this person caught between</u></b> <b><u>the muses of tragedy and comedy. This person directed the Smock Alley Theater after serving for five</u></b> <b><u>years in a company at Drury Lane. This person came to prominence in the (+)</u> title role of Richard the Third and helped to ensure the enduring legacy of the author of works such as </b><em><b>Hamlet</b></em><b>. (*) </b>For the points, name this 18th century English theatre manager and actor, who is remembered as his generation's most prominent interpreter of William Shakespeare.", "answer": "David <b><u>Garrick</u></b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "<b><u>The Twelfth Article of this treaty called for the preservation of \u201cthe full and entire enjoyment</u></b> <b><u>of all Property,\" which one side\u2019s members gained from another. Jules Favre was criticized for his</u></b> <b><u>role in this treaty, which gave rise to a set of \u201clost provinces.\u201d An indemnity payment of five billion</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> francs was established in this treaty, which mandated emigration or change of citizenship for inhabitants of Alsace-Lorraine. Effectively ending the (*) </b>Franco-Prussian War in 1871, for the points, what is this treaty?", "answer": "Treaty of <b><u>Frankfurt</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This person is depicted standing jubilantly over a drunk man in a cartoon captioned \"Whither</u></b> <b><u>are we drifting?\" John Abbott succeeded this person in a position in which he introduced a</u></b> <b><u>controversial head tax on Chinese immigrants, three years after a (+)</u> neighboring country introduced a similar Exclusion Act. This politician, considered to be among the Fathers of the Confederation, authorized the execution of (*) </b>Louis Riel. For the points, identify this Scottish-born politician who served most of 1867 to 1891 as the first prime minister of Canada.", "answer": "John A(lexander) <b><u>Macdonald</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>One line from this song titles an Arthur La Bern novel that was the basis for the Alfred</u></b> <b><u>Hitchcock film</u> </b><em><b><u>Frenzy</u></b></em><b><u>. This song, which was written by Jack Judge and Harry Williams, was made</u></b> <b><u>famous due to a recording by tenor John McCormack. (+)</u> This song's second verse says that \"Paddy wrote a letter to his Irish Molly-O\" and begins by saying, \"Up to mighty London came an Irishman one day.\" (*) </b>For the points, name this Irish music hall song that was made popular as a marching song by British soldiers in World War One.", "answer": "\"It's a <b><u>Long Way to Tipperary</u></b>\" (or \"It's a <b><u>Long, Long Way to Tipperary</u></b>\")", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>This speech notes how one person \"endured the icy and piercing blasts of northwestern</u></b> <b><u>winters\" and went \"wading through the deep and cold waters and black swamps of Michigan and</u></b> <b><u>upper Canada.\" This 1840 speech by</u> (+)Charles Ogle is alternatively known as \"The Regal Splendor of the President's (*) </b>Palace,\" and sought to depict one politician as an elitist. For the points, name this oration that targeted Martin Van Buren and was titled for an idiom referencing his luxurious lifestyle.", "answer": "<b><u>Gold Spoon</u></b> Oration (accept <b><u>The Regal Splendor of the President's Palace</u></b> before \"Regal\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Peace accords negotiated in this city led to Jacques-Roger Booh-Booh overseeing a coalition</u></b> <b><u>government that fell apart after Cyprien Ntaryamira and Juv\u00e9nal Habyarimana were killed in a shot</u></b> <b><u>down plane. (+)</u> A speech in this city announced nine principles of \"African socialism\" as the new platform of the TANU party, which the speaker called </b><em><b>Ujaama</b></em><b>. Naming a set of accords intended to prevent civil war in (*) </b>Rwanda, for the points, what is this Tanzanian city that names a \"Declaration\" by Julius Nyrere?", "answer": "<b><u>Arusha</u></b> (accept <b><u>Arusha</u></b> Accords; accept <b><u>Arusha</u></b> Declaration)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The</u> </b><em><b><u>Uttarapurana</u></b></em><b><u> claims that this person hailed from the Videha-ruled city of Kundalpur in</u></b> <b><u>Bihar. The historicity of this person often involves the analysis of the text of the</u> </b><em><b><u>Kalpa Sutra</u></b></em><b><u>, and this</u></b> <b><u>person is associated with a faith system whose sects include the (+)</u> \u015av\u0113t\u0101mbara. This son of Trishala and Siddhartha was the successor of Parshvanatha, and was claimed by Hemachandra to be older than the Buddha. (*) </b>For the points, name this major figure in Jainism, considered the last of the <em>Tirthankaras</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Mahavir</u></b>a (accept <b><u>Vardhaman</u></b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b><u>Cardinal Thomas Wolsey imposed a curfew prior to this event, which began after aldermen</u></b> <b><u>failed to force two young apprentices back into their homes in Cheapside. John Lincoln was executed</u></b> <b><u>for this event, which was preceded by a speech given at (+)</u> St. Paul's Cross by a man known as \"Dr. Bell.\" Following this event, Catherine of Aragon begged King Henry the Eighth to pardon the lives of the (*) </b>rebels. For the points, name this xenophobic riot of apprentices and other laborers that occurred on an eponymous day in 1517.", "answer": "<b><u>Evil May Day</u></b> (or <b><u>Ill May Day</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This person examined the ties between Kojo Annan and Cotecna Inspection SA after the</u></b> <b><u>investigation of potential corruption in the Oil for Food program. This person succeeded Jeffrey</u></b> <b><u>Immelt as the chair of the President's (+)</u> Economic Recovery Advisory Board. This person's namesake rule applies to restrictions banning certain types of speculative investments that came into effect in 2015. Serving under the (*) </b>Carter and Reagan administrations, for the points, what man preceded Alan Greenspan as chair of the Federal Reserve from 1979 to 1987?", "answer": "Paul <b><u>Volcker</u></b> Jr. (or Paul Adolph <b><u>Volcker</u></b> Jr.)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>In 1912, this political party rigged a parliamentary poll that became known as the \"Election of</u></b> <b><u>Clubs.\" In 1913, this political party launched a raid that resulted in the overthrow of the Freedom and</u></b> <b><u>Accord Party, as well as the assassination of the minister of war. (+)</u> The government of this political party refused to sign the Treaty of London, and this party reduced the role of Abdul Hamid the Second to that of a figurehead. (*) </b>For the points, name this nationalist party in Ottoman Turkey that was led by the Three Pashas.", "answer": "Committee of <b><u>Union and Progress</u></b> (or <b><u>\u0130ttihad ve Terakki</u></b> Cemiyeti [[JE-mee-YEH-tee]]; or <b><u>Firkasi</u></b>; accept <b><u>CUP</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This person started their political career by running against Richard J. Daley for Mayor of</u></b> <b><u>Chicago in 1967, and this person was a write-in candidate for the Peace and Freedom Party in the</u></b> <b><u>1968 presidential election. Dr. Benjamin (+)</u> Spock was this person\u2019s running mate in Virginia and Pennsylvania in 1968. This person admitted to \u201creceiving the first really good beating I ever had in my life\u201d while jailed in Birmingham, Alabama in 1963. (*)</b> For the points, name this pioneering African-American comedian nicknamed the \u201cBlack Mort Stahl.\"", "answer": "Dick <b><u>Gregory</u></b> (or Richard Claxton <b><u>Gregory</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Peace in this region has been undermined by factions including the Sadio and Badiatte. This</u></b> <b><u>region was once the home of the Kasa Kingdom of the Bainuk people, and that kingdom in this region</u></b> <b><u>had its capital at Brikama. A Catholic priest born to a (+)</u> Serer father fought for separatism in this region, and that priest, Augustin Diamacoune Senghor, signed a 2004 treaty concerning this region with President Abdoulaye Wade, the predecessor of (*) </b>Macky Sall. For the points, name this disputed region of Senegal that was once ruled by the Wolof kingdoms.", "answer": "<b><u>Casamance</u></b> (or <b><u>Casamansa</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Each verse of this song ends with a line stating, \"Yet let's be content, and the times lament.\"</u></b> <b><u>The lyrics to this song were first published in the 1640s and initially served to protest a</u></b> <b><u>Parliamentary ban on celebrating Christmas. A musical that won the (+)</u> 2016 Pulitzer Prize for Drama describes this song as \"the drinking song they're singing\" during a sword exchange between Charles O'Hara and Benjamin (*)</b> Lincoln. For the points, name this English ballad that was apocryphally played by British forces when Charles Cornwallis surrendered at Yorktown.", "answer": "\"The <b><u>World Turned Upside Down</u></b>\"", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>The leader of the Peloponnesian League was a holder of this office, and these officials formally</u></b> <b><u>declared war at meetings of the</u> </b><em><b><u>crypteia</u></b></em><b><u>. These members of a council of (+)</u> five were opposed by Cleomenes, but provided a balance to their city's Heraclid royal family. Unlike the </b><em><b>Gerousia</b></em><b>, these officials, whose name means \"overseer,\" were elected for a year, rather than serving their term for life. Both Agiad and Eurypontid monarchs acted as generals under, (*) </b>for the points, what board of elected magistrates of Sparta?", "answer": "<b><u>Ephor</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>As a major in the U.S. Army, this figure led the Sacramento River massacre, Klamath Lake</u></b> <b><u>massacre, and the Sutter Buttes massacre. This person faced a court martial after a dispute over the</u></b> <b><u>rightful military governor of one (+)</u> western territory but was reinstated by James K. Polk. Abraham Lincoln removed this person as commander of the Department of the West for insubordination after this person issued an unapproved edict of (*) </b>emancipation. For the points, name this first Republican presidential nominee based in California, nicknamed the \"Great Pathfinder.\"", "answer": "John C(harles) <b><u>Fr\u00e9mont</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>One leader at this battle was hit in the mouth with an arrow as he was drinking water from a</u></b> <b><u>river. This battle, which occurred after an army was intercepted while headed toward Kufa, preceded</u></b> <b><u>the Second Fitna. Self-flagellation is commonly practiced on the last of a (+)</u> ten-day period of mourning that commemorates this 680 C.E. battle which pitted an Umayyad Caliph against a grandson of Ali named Husayn. Commemorated during (*) </b>Muharram, for the points, what was this battle of particular significance in Shi'a Islam?", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Karbala</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In a folksong from Sule Skerry, one of these creatures proposes to a wetnurse who sings while</u></b> <b><u>weaning a baby. In one tale, a male one of these creatures seduces a woman named Ursilla, who gives</u></b> <b><u>birth to children with (+)</u> webbed fingers and toes. Undines and sirens share the domain of these creatures, who were said to constantly gaze at the sea and would abandon their husband and children if they found their skin and could return to their (*) </b>seal form. For the points, name these shapeshifting water spirits from Celtic folklore.", "answer": "<b><u>Selkie</u></b>s (prompt on \"seal folk\" before \"seal\")", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "<b><u>In a position he held for over 31 years, this person succeeded Charles Evans Whittaker. This</u></b> <b><u>person worked as the chair of Colorado for the 1960 presidential campaign of John F. Kennedy before</u></b> <b><u>going on to become U.S. deputy (+)</u> attorney general. Once a clerk for Fred Vinson, this person wrote such majority opinions as those in </b><em><b>Planned Parenthood v. Casey</b></em><b> and </b><em><b>Bowers v. Hardwick</b></em><b>. (*) </b>For the points, name this Supreme Court justice who once led the league in rushing yards while playing in the NFL.", "answer": "Byron <b><u>White</u></b> (or Byron Raymond \"Whizzer\" <b><u>White</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>An original run of 200 copies of this work was published by Philippe Denis Pierres while its</u></b> <b><u>author was serving as a trade representative. This book was the only full-length work by the author</u></b> <b><u>of a</u> </b><em><b><u>Manual of Parliamentary Practice for the Use of the Senate of the United States</u></b></em><b><u>. (+)</u> The earliest version of this work was completed in 1781 and includes chapters on the sea ports, boundaries, and rivers of its title (*)</b> state. For the points, name this book written by Thomas Jefferson about, and in celebration of, his home state.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Notes on the State of Virginia</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>A lunar dog may be the subject of a stirrup spout vessel known as this culture's namesake</u></b> <b><u>\"Crawling Feline.\" This culture's chief deity was a being called Ai apaec</u> </b>[['EYE' AY-pake]]<b><u>, who is</u></b> <b><u>sometimes known as the \"headsman.\" The Lady of Cao is a (+)</u> mummified woman from this culture, which also built a brick pyramid called Huaca del Sol. With a capital that is now located in the modern province of Trujillo [[troo-HEE-yoh]], this is, (*) </b>for the points, what ancient civilization sometimes known as the Proto-Chim\u00fa that flourished from 100 to 700 CE in northern Peru?", "answer": "<b><u>Moche</u></b> [[MOH-cheh]] (accept <b><u>Mochica</u></b> Culture; accept <b><u>Early Chimu</u></b> or <b><u>Pre-Chimu</u></b> or <b><u>Proto-</u><u>Chim\u00fa</u></b> before \"Proto-Chimu\" is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Testimony given by this person implicated Josef Peters in the disappearance of Juliet Stuart</u></b> <b><u>Poyntz. This person served in an editorial position at such publications as</u> </b><em><b><u>New Masses</u></b></em><b><u>,</u> </b><em><b><u>The Daily</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Worker</u></b></em><b><u>, and</u> </b><em><b><u>Time Magazine</u></b></em><b><u>. This person aided Richard (+)</u> Nixon\u2019s investigation of Alger Hiss, a State Department employee, by producing a hollowed-out pumpkin that contained evidence of government information shared with (*) </b>Soviet operatives. For the points, name this reformed-Communist editor of the <em>National Review</em>.", "answer": "Whittaker <b><u>Chambers</u></b> (or Jay Vivian <b><u>Chambers</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This event was sparked by the summoning of militia to Fort James to defend against Native</u></b> <b><u>American attacks, and the leader of this event sent Jost Stoll and Matthew Clarkson to London to</u></b> <b><u>normalize one situation. Francis Nicholson was deposed through this event, the leader of which was</u></b> <b><u>blamed for the (+)</u> Schenectady Massacre. Opposed by Colonel Henry Sloughter, who was commissioned by William the Third, and led by a namesake (*) </b>German-American militia captain in colonial New York, for the points, what was this rebellion?", "answer": "<b><u>Leisler</u></b>'s Rebellion (accept synonyms like \"Revolt\" or \"Uprising\" in place of \"Rebellion\"; accept Jacob <b><u>Leisler</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A recounting of the myth of Adapa was among the findings at this location, which was referred</u></b> <b><u>to by H. G. Wells in</u> </b><em><b><u>Outline of History</u></b></em><b><u> as \"the most precious source of historical material in the world.\"</u></b> <b><u>The archaeological site of Kouyunjik where this location was found corresponds to the ancient city</u></b> <b><u>of (+)</u> Nineveh. Among the over 30,000 clay tablets held in this location is a copy of the </b><em><b>Epic of </b></em><b>(*) </b><em>Gilgamesh</em>. For the points, identify this significant collection of texts named for a king of the Assyrian Empire.", "answer": "Royal <b><u>Library</u></b> of <b><u>Ashurbanipal</u></b> (both portions required)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This author, who used pen names including \"Saxe Holm,\" published the poetry collections</u></b> <em><b><u>Easter Bells</u></b></em><b><u> and</u> </b><em><b><u>Letters from a Cat</u></b></em><b><u>. Inspired by the marriage of Hugo and Victoria Reid, this person</u></b> <b><u>wrote an 1884 novel about a Scottish-Native American orphan. After attending a lecture from (+)</u></b> <b>Standing Bear, this person wrote a work they sent to every member of Congress with the quote, \"Look on your hands: they are stained with the blood of your relations.\" The author of </b><em><b>Ramona</b></em><b> and (*) </b><em>A</em> <em>Century of Dishonor</em>, for the points, who was this activist?", "answer": "Helen <b><u>Hunt</u><u>Jackson</u></b> (or H. H. <b><u>Jackson</u></b>; or Helen Maria <b><u>Fiske</u></b>; accept either underlined portion)", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "<b><u>This empire's downfall was possibly due to the switch in allegiances by the Gilani brothers,</u></b> <b><u>and the Tuluva Dynasty once ruled this empire, first established by Harihara the First. Along with</u></b> <b><u>Chittor's Rana Sangha, a leader of this empire, named Krishnadevaraya, was considered by Babur (+)</u></b> <b>to be the greatest Hindu king of India. Speaking Kannada and sharing its name with a district that was once part of the Madras presidency, (*) </b>for the points, what was this Indian empire, led from Vellore?", "answer": "<b><u>Vijayanagar</u></b>a Empire (accept <b><u>Karnata</u></b> in place of <b><u>Vijayanagar</u></b>a; accept \"Kingdom\" in place of \"Empire\"; accept <b><u>Vijayanagar</u></b>a District)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>These measures barred members of the Burschenschaften [[bur-shehn-SHAF-tehn]] and</u></b> <b><u>Turnerschaften from attending universities and significantly weakened fraternities. These measures</u></b> <b><u>called for the establishment of a commission to investigate (+)</u> revolutionary conspiracies, such as the attempt on the life of Karl von Ibell, and events contributing to the passage of these measures included the assassination of conservative dramatist August von Kotzebue [[KAHT-suh-buh]]. Klemens von (*) </b>Metternich sponsored, for the points, what anti-dissidence restrictions that were named for a spa town in Bohemia?", "answer": "<b><u>Carlsbad</u></b> Decrees (or <b><u>Karlsbader</u></b> Beschl\u00fcsse)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Italian Capuchin missionary Antonio Cavazzi served in the court of this ruler, and, despite</u></b> <b><u>allying with the Dutch, this ruler failed to take the Fortress of Massangano in a 1640 battle. One</u></b> <b><u>popular story says that when a foreign governor only provided this person a mat to sit on, this</u></b> <b><u>Ambundu (+)</u> sat on a kneeling slave girl as a chair. Marrying a warlord from the Imbangala group and fighting against early Portuguese colonization of Angola in the 17th century as ruler of the Nodongo and Matamba, (*) </b>for the points, who was this queen?", "answer": "<b><u>Nzinga</u></b> of Ndongo and Matamba (or <b><u>Nzinga</u></b> Ana de Sousa Mbande)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Lee Johnson wrote a piece on \"The Etruscan Sources of\" this painting, which contains column</u></b> <b><u>capitals that William Steinke claims were inspired by a temple in Bombay. An elephant's head can be</u></b> <b><u>found in this painting, which was inspired by a Lord (+)</u> Byron play based on the historical accounts of Diodorus Siculus. A servant in this painting is depicted in the act of stabbing a woman who may be a concubine of the (*) </b>central figure. For the points, name this painting by Eug\u00e8ne Delacroix that depicts the last moments of an Assyrian king.", "answer": "<em>The</em> <em><b><u>Death of Sardanapalus</u></b></em> (accept <em>La</em> <em><b><u>Mort de Sardanapale</u></b></em>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>In the Idaho cities of Sugar City and Lincoln, one part of this program refused to engage in beet</u></b> <b><u>harvesting due to the wage difference compared to potato picking. This program, which was initiated</u></b> <b><u>to address a wartime shortage in certain industries, derives its name from a (+)</u> Spanish word translating as \"manual labor.\" This program began in 1942 after one country signed a Farm Labor Agreement with the U.S. (*) </b>For the points, identify this program that brought Mexican railroad and agricultural workers into the United States.", "answer": "<b><u>Bracero</u></b> Program", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Frank Speck's work has been used as the basis to conclude that the name of these people</u></b> <b><u>means \"the destroyers.\" One man described making a fort named for these people \"a fiery Oven\"</u></b> <b><u>during a conflict that resulted in many of these people being sent to (+)</u> Bermuda. These people were attacked by John Mason's forces during the Mystic Massacre. In the 1600s, the Mohegan split off from, (*)</b> for the points, what Native American people whose namesake war was fought against members of the Plymouth and Massachusetts Bay colonies?", "answer": "<b><u>Pequot</u></b> [[PEE-kwaht]] (accept <b><u>Pequot</u></b> War)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Eljigidei [[el-JIH-geh-deh]] was put to death for allegedly attempting to nullify the election of</u></b> <b><u>this leader, whose appointment of Masud Beg in Turkestan was one of the nine provincial leadership</u></b> <b><u>positions he gave to Muslims. The kingdom of (+)</u> Dali in modern-day Yunnan was captured under this leader, thanks in part to the efforts of a future leader who would found a capital at Dadu and host Marco Polo. The earliest khagan to hail from the line of (*)</b> Tolui was, for the points, what predecessor to Kublai Khan and fourth Khagan of the Mongol Empire?", "answer": "<b><u>M\u00f6ngke</u></b> Khan (or <b><u>M\u00f6nkh</u></b> Khagan; or <b><u>M\u00e9ngg\u0113</u></b> Khan; prompt on \"Khan\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This island's village of Aidipsos [['EYE'-dip-sohs]] is a resort known for its ancient hot springs</u></b> <b><u>and spas. This island is home to the Iseion, a temple to the Egyptian god Isis, and the Temple of Apollo</u></b> <b><u>Daphnephoros in its ancient city of Eretria. This island's capital of (+)</u> Chalkida, which was known as Chalcis in antiquity, claims to be home to Europe's oldest continuous Jewish community. The Euripus Strait separates Boeotia from, (*) </b>for the points, what second-largest Greek island, a narrow island located east of Athens?", "answer": "<b><u>Euboea</u></b> (or <b><u>Evia</u></b>; or <b><u>E\u00faboia</u></b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>Robert Todd flanked a Canadian force at this battle, in which Jean Francois Hamtramck led an</u></b> <b><u>advance after a charge by Robert Campbell's dragoons. In this battle, William Campbell closed the</u></b> <b><u>doors of Fort Miami after the (+)</u> Odawa chief Turkey Foot was sniped while speaking from a rock. This battle led to the signing of the Treaty of Greenville and the withdrawal of the British from the southern (*) </b>Great Lakes. For the points, name this 1794 battle in which Little Turtle was defeated by \"Mad\" Anthony Wayne in Ohio.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Fallen Timbers</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In one work, this artist captured her sister Edma watching her infant daughter, Jeanne. This</u></b> <b><u>artist is shown looking off to the left while accompanied by the violinist Fanny Claus and the painter</u></b> <b><u>Jean Baptiste Antoine Guillemet [[GWEE-meh]] in the painting (+)</u></b> <em><b>The Balcony</b></em><b>. Along with Marie Bracquemond and Mary Cassatt, this artist was considered one of the \"trois [[TWAH]] grande (*) </b>dames\" of a certain genre. For the points, name this French impressionist artist of <em>The Cradle</em>, the sister-in-law of Edouard Manet.", "answer": "Berthe <b><u>Morisot</u></b> [[mor-ih-SOH]] (or Berthe Marie Pauline <b><u>Morisot</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>Wang Laboratories, which led an economic miracle, moved from Tewksbury to this city, where</u></b> <b><u>its large Cambodian population led to the film</u> </b><em><b><u>Monkey Dance</u></b></em><b><u>. This city's namesake poetry journal,</u></b> <b><u>the</u> </b><em><b><u>Offering</u></b></em><b><u>, featured works by Lucy Larcom and Sarah Bagley. This city and (+)</u> Waltham named one industry's production and labor system, and this city employed namesake \"mill girls.\" (*) </b>For the points, name this Massachusetts city, which was named for businessman Francis Cabot and known for its textile mills in the Industrial Revolution.", "answer": "<b><u>Lowell</u></b> (accept <em><b><u>Lowell</u></b> Offering</em>; accept Waltham-<b><u>Lowell</u></b> System)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This emperor closed Chang'an [[chahng-AHN]] to search for evil sorcerers, an initiative that</u></b> <b><u>involved this emperor executing 300 people, including his own daughter. This emperor\u2019s prime</u></b> <b><u>minister, Gongsun Hong [[GOHNG-swuhn HOHNG]], persuaded him to create the (+)</u> first imperial university with five teachers and 50 students. This emperor dug a huge artificial lake to train the imperial navy while not engaged with the Xiongnu [[SHEE-oong NOO]]. (*) </b>For the point name this emperor who waged wars that doubled the area of Han China.", "answer": "Emperor <b><u>Wu</u></b> of Han (or Han <b><u>Wudi</u></b>; or <b><u>Liu Che</u></b>; accept <b><u>Tong</u></b>; prompt on \"Martial Emperor\"; prompt on \"Warrior Emperor\"; do NOT accept or prompt on \"Wu Zetian\" or \"Empress Wu\"))", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This person left a Tennessee law practice after shooting Andrew Jackson in a barroom brawl,</u></b> <b><u>during which this person was stabbed five times. Ironically, this person earlier served as Jackson\u2019s</u></b> <b><u>aide de camp during the War of 1812. This politician was the first person to serve in the Senate for</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> 30 years, in which role he gained the nickname \u201cOld Bullion\u201d for his opposition to paper money. This father in law of John C. Fr\u00e9mont shares a name with his great-great nephew, a painter and mentor of Jackson Pollock. (*)</b> For the points, name this politician whose anti-slavery stance cost him re-election in Missouri.", "answer": "Thomas Hart <b><u>Benton</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The</u> </b><em><b><u>Society</u></b></em><b><u> engaged in a resupply mission for participants carrying out this plan, which</u></b> <b><u>William Paterson is thought to have originally proposed. A site in what is now Vieques [[vyeh-KEZ]],</u></b> <b><u>Puerto Rico was brought under European control as part of this plan, whose (+)</u> inability to be implemented as intended contributed to the Acts of Union. This 1698 to 1700 plan involved one nation's attempt to establish New (*) </b>Caledonia. For the point, name this unsuccessful plan by Scotland to create a colony on the Isthmus of Panama.", "answer": "<b><u>Darien</u></b> Scheme (prompt on \"Scottish colonization of the New World\" or \"Scottish Colonization of Panama\" or similar answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>After studying economics, this person served under Minister for Local Government and</u></b> <b><u>Administrative Services Tom Uren. Bill Shorten and Tony Burke were among the members of the</u></b> <b><u>Shadow Ministry of this person, who claimed to be the only person with a (+)</u> \"non-Anglo Celtic name\" to run for one office. In 2013, this person became the Labor Party's deputy leader, and, in 2022, this person reached his highest position after succeeding (*) </b>Scott Morrison. For the points, identify this current prime minister of Australia.", "answer": "Anthony <b><u>Albanese</u></b> (or Anthony Norman <b><u>Albanese</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>Eliot Daniel wrote the theme for this television show, which was nearly spun-off with William</u></b> <b><u>Frawley and Vivian Vance. The production company for this television show was a portmanteau of its</u></b> <b><u>founders and was known as</u> (+) Desilu Productions. This television show was timed so that the pregnancy of the actress playing the (*) </b>main character would coincide with the introduction of Ricky Ricardo Jr. For the points, name this influential sitcom of the 1950s, which featured Desi Arnaz and his wife, the namesake star of the show.", "answer": "<em><b><u>I Love Lucy</u></b></em> (do NOT accept \"<em>The Lucy Show</em>\")", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>One politician from this country, who also served as its justice minister and as leader of the</u></b> <b><u>PPSD, was Moumin Farah. In the midst of a 2015 military intervention involving two other countries,</u></b> <b><u>Indian nationals were evacuated to this country from Yemen. Camp (+)</u> Lemonnier, the sole permanent U.S. military base in Africa, was established in this country, which is currently led by Isma\u00efl Omar Guelleh. Formerly known as the French Territory of the Afars and Issas, (*) </b>for the points, what is this country in the Horn of Africa named for its capital?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Djibouti</u></b> (or Jamhuuriyadda <b><u>Jabuuti</u></b>)  <b>Extra Questions </b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>During an Olympic marathon in this city, Thomas Hicks won while suffering hallucinations</u></b> <b><u>after his trainers fed him strychnine and raw eggs. This city was the first to pair the Olympics with</u></b> <b><u>human zoos in what were dubbed \u201cAnthropology Days.\u201d (+)</u> This city became the host of those Olympics after threatening to undermine Chicago's bid by hosting their own athletic competition during a World's Fair. (*) </b>For the points, name this Midwestern city that simultaneously hosted the 1904 Summer Olympics and the Louisiana Purchase Exposition.", "answer": "<b><u>St. Louis</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A rival claimant to this ruler\u2019s throne, who mysteriously disappeared after being taken to</u></b> <b><u>Rouen, was Arthur of Brittany. This ruler lost control of Anjou and Normandy during a series of wars</u></b> <b><u>in which they fought (+)</u> Philip the Second. This youngest child of Eleanor of Aquitaine was the brother of a man who fought the siege of Acre against Saladin during the (*) </b>Third Crusade. A group of barons forced this ruler to sign a \u201cGreat Charter\u201d at Runnymede in 1215. For the points, name this king of England who signed the Magna Carta.", "answer": "King <b><u>John</u></b> the First of England (accept <b><u>John</u></b> Lackland)", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}